Guide to the Richard L. Gilbert Advertising Collection 1960's-1970's PR 309
New-York Historical Society
Richard L. Gilbert Advertising Collection
1960's-1970's
New-York Historical Society
PR 309
3.01 Linear feet (2 boxes)
90 print advertisements and proofs by Richard L. Gilbert's advertising agency from the 1960's and 1970's.
Arrangement
This collection is housed in two boxes, according to size, and organized into folders by client/product.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 90 laminated proofs and advertisements created by the Gilbert Agency in the 1960's and 1970's. The advertisements are arranged by client/product names, which are specifically identified in the box and folder list.
Emblematic of the "creative revolution" that changed the face of advertising in the 1960's, these ads are characterized by humor, irony and irreverence. Notable examples include an After Six advertisement offering Russian Premier Alexi Kosygin a free tuxedo ("For you, we'll make it up in red"); a Renault ad pitched to "people who swore they would never buy another one"; and a London Fog ad picturing a man and a woman on an ark full of animals (mostly borrowed from the 1964 World's Fair African exhibit) with the tagline "When it looks like rain, believe in London Fog."
The collection provides an interesting window into the popular culture of the 1960's and early 1970's. It also reflects the social issues of the time, in particular the anti-war movement, which features in several advertising campaigns (Some Toys Don't Like War, for Georg Jensen, and a series of political ads urging a vote on the war).
Biographical / Historical
Richard L. Gilbert was born in the Bronx on March 23, 1921. After attending DeWitt Clinton High School and City College of New York, he was drafted into the Army in 1942.
After his discharge from the Army in 1946, Gilbert returned to New York, working various jobs in the advertising industry. In 1950, Gilbert opened his own firm, Gilbert Advertising, in an office on West 31st Street. Over the next 40 years, Gilbert's firm compiled an impressive roster of high-profile clients, including Anne Klein, London Fog, Renault, and the Metropolitan Opera. Although it remained a small agency, the firm created some high-impact ad campaigns, most notably Some Toys Hate War, an anti-Vietnam war-themed ad for silversmith Georg Jensen.
More information about Gilbert's career can be found in his memoir, Marching Up Madison Avenue, also held in the collection. Originally published in 2008, the book was re-issued in 2013 with the title I Was a Mad Man: A Madison Avenue Memoir.
A long-time resident of the Bronx neighborhood Riverdale, Gilbert became a frequent contributor to the "Point of View" column in the Riverdale Press after retiring from advertising. He died at home on December 29, 2013.
Access restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Provenance
Gift of Richard Gilbert, 2013.
- After Six tuxedos, 1960's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Anti-war ads, 1970's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- Barton's Chocolates, circa 1960's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Berlitz language school, circa 1960's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Charles of the Ritz cosmetics, 1970's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Club Med vacations, 1969-1970's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Georg Jensen store, 1969-1970's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- Gold Seal beverages (includes Gold Seal champagne, Mateus wine, Tuborg beer, and Dubonnet), circa 1960's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Guerlain perfumes, 1960's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Israel Government Tourist Office, 1960's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
- London Fog coats, 1960's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Metropolitan Opera, 1970's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Movado watches, circa 1960's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Renault, 1960's (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Shoes (Gamins, Andrew Geller, Portage, Nunn Bush, Weyenberg Massagic), 1960's-1970's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- SOS cleaning products, 1970's (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- "Marching Up Madison Avenue," by Richard L. Gilbert, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)